Clara E. Laughlin Papers, 1903-1932
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Clara E. Laughlin papers
1903-1932
Laughlin, Clara E. (Clara Elizabeth), 1873-1941
MS 91
8 boxes (5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Author; Travel specialist; Journalist; Editor; Radio broadcaster. Papers include personal and professional correspondence; manuscripts and some published works of the "So You're Going To..." travel series, radio talks, and biographical writings on Sarah Bernhardt, Marshal Foch and James Whitcomb Riley; clippings; reviews; and photographs.
Biographical Note
Clara Elizabeth Laughlin (1873-1941) was born in New York City and attended school in Chicago. She graduated from Chicago High School in 1890; did not attend college. She was literary editor for The Interior (Chicago) from age 18 for 10 years; and author of over 35 books. She contributed to many literary magazines and was a manuscript reader and literary advisor for several publishers. She gave weekly radio talks on travel for the Chicago Daily News station in the 1920s, and founded Clara Laughlin Travel Services, circa 1922, specializing in foreign travel advice for women. Laughlin published the travel series, So you're going to...; and edited the So You're Going news travel magazine. Other writings include biographies, historical subjects, novels, short stories, and plays.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Papers include a small amount of personal and professional correspondence; manuscripts of articles and the travel series So You're Going To... books; manuscript of Laughlin's autobiography, Traveling Through Life (1934); radio talks on cruises and various travel programs; biographical writings on Sarah Bernhardt, Marshal Foch and James Whitcomb Riley; talks at the Chicago Art Institute on the Thorne Miniature American Rooms; clippings of reviews of published works and a column for the Hearst papers; memorabilia; photographs; and copies of some of her published books.
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
The Clara E. Laughlin Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by her nieces Mary Clara Laughlin and Betty Laughlin Sweeney in 1959.
Search Terms
Laughlin, Clara E. (Clara Elizabeth), 1873-1941; Authors, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; Businesswomen--United States--Biography--Sources; Chicago (Ill.)--History--Sources; Europe--Description and travel--Sources; Europe-Guidebooks--Sources; Mediterranean region--Description and travel--Sources; Tourism--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Travel agents--United States--Biography--Sources; Travel writers--Biography--Sources; Voyages and travels--History--20th century--Sources; Women editors--United States--Biography--Sources; Women owned business enterprises--United States--History--Sources; Women travelers--History--20th century--Sources
- Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Biographical material 1913-1925, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photographs 1907-1910, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing 1921, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Incoming, A-Z 1913-58 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Clippings
  - The Heart of Her Highness 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous 1903-41 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Writings
  - Radio talks
    - Cruises (typescripts) 1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Travel (typescripts) 1925 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Manuscriptn.d. (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Articles
    - Chicago Gordon Club 1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chicago's social conditions 1917-18 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Child psychology, 191 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - France and Medal of Honor Notification 1923 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Girlsn.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Men Are Like That" n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Quits Crime to Go Straight And Makes Good As Promised" 1919? (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous 1917-40 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Robert Lusk case 1917 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Biography
      - Sarah Bernhardt 1918, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - James Whitcomb Riley 1916, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Marshall Ferdinand Foch (includes correspondence) 1918-19 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Serial: "The Winds of Waynesburg" n.d. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Short storiesn.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Miniature American Rooms," 1941-1944 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Manuscripts
    - "So You're Going to Europe" (Ladies Home Journal) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - So You're Going to Italy
      - Last draft (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Proofs (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Original manuscript (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - Italy (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Germany, Austria (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Scotland (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
    - Spain (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - So You're Going to the Mediterranean (Box 5)
    - Traveling Through Life (autobiography) 1934 (Box 5)
    - So You're Going to Paris (Box 6, Folder 2-6)
    - French pamphlets (Box 6)
    - Where It All Comes True (Box 6)
      - In France (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - In Italy (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - In Scandinavia (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - In Switzerland (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - So You're Going Southn.d. (Box 7)
    - The Golden Fleecen.d. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - The Ruby Drops of Ninonn.d. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Travels in Englandn.d. (Box 8)
- Books (by Clara Laughlin)
  - Everybody's Birthright: A Vision Of Jeanne d'Arc, New York 1914 (Box 8)
  - Everybody's Lonesome, London 1911 (Box 8)
  - The Martyred Towns Of France, New York 1919 (Box 8)
  - Reminiscences Of James Whitcomb Riley, New York 1916 (Box 8)
  - So You're Going To Germany And Austria, Boston 1930 (Box 8)
  - So You're Going To Scandinavia, London 1938 (Box 8)
  - So You're Going To The Mediterranean!, Boston 1935 (Box 8)
  - So You're Going To Travel, Boston 1938 (Box 8)
  - Stories Of Authors' Loves, London 1905 (Box 8)
  - The Work-A-Day Girl, New York 1913 (Box 8)